Guide to the Alexander Addison Papers, 1786-1803 DAR.1925.06
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Correspondence from Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, 1786-1803; III.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, October 21, 1786 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Nisbet replies to Addison's request for advice on his career and strongly discourages him from leaving the clergy to become a lawyer. Nisbet argues that reasonable educated clergy are the only hope for America.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, December 7, 1787 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Nisbet tells Addison that he respects his decision to become a lawyer, despite Nisbet's advice. He discusses the [Federal Constitutional] Convention and criticizes Pennsylvania's lack of support of its government. Nisbet supports the Constitution.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, November 5, 1790 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Writing to Addison, Nisbet apologizes for not visiting him in western Pennsylvania. He recommends Richard Henderson, a recent seminary graduate, for a teaching position near Addison's home. Additionally, he derides revolutionary trends in European politics.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, July 22, 1791 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    In his letter, Nisbet discusses the effect of the French revolutions and their ill-advised support by some Americans, particularly [Paine] and Franklin.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, September 29, 1791 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Nisbet congratulates Addison on his appointment as judge. He remarks on the hypocrisy of Pennsylvanian and American response to slave revolts in St. Domingo [Dominican Republic] and criticizes Paine for not considering the rights of slaves. Nisbet predicts the fate of the French royal family and compares the French, Polish, and American revolutions.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, November 12, 1791 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Nisbet writes to Addison to recommend an acquaintance, Mr. Wilson, for any teaching positions near Addison. He describes the political situations in Poland and France and again refers to slave uprisings in Hispaniola [Haiti/Dominican Republic], and the ideological shortcomings of [Paine] Payne's writing.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, December 26, 1791 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Nisbet thanks Addison for finding Mr. Wilson a ministerial and teaching position. He criticizes the inability of officials to govern the frontier, especially from a distance, and writes unsympathetically about both Washington and Adams as current and prospective presidents. Nisbet also criticizes Brackenridge's opposition to the Constitution.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, May 10, 1792 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    References are made to a recent disturbance in western Pennsylvania and the previous massacre of "Moravian Indians." Nisbet discusses an inquiry into General Sinclair's conduct and the appointment of General Wayne as commander in chief of the Army. He criticizes debate in the Congress about its form and function. He discusses predictions of a Prussian-assisted counter-revolution in France and goes on to describe bankruptcies in New York.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, May 11, 1792 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Nisbet shares, in confidence, his problems with the Trustees of Dickinson College. He describes and criticizes the character of American students and education and critiques European books on American society and education.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, April 16, 1793 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Findley talks about the armament of the land and sea by the French mob against Great Britain. He said that his will deprive the English mob for any correspondence with the French National Convention and Jacobin Club. The French mob was ordered to leave London when British Court received advice of the murder of the King. They must now conquer all Europe or be knocked on the head by the combined powers. He also describe that if Great Britain is drawn in to a war with this country, it is by it own stupidity of our politicians, we soon be freed from Indians to be occupied by English Garrisons.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, June 11, 1793 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Nisbet writes that he is thankful that Addison hasn't had problems with Indians, despite Indian conflicts [Chickamauga Wars] in the south. He writes of his hopes that [western Pennsylvanians] are still in opposition to the Excise Act. Nisbet discusses European politics, especially the war between England and France, and revolutionary developments in France.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, June 14, 1793 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Nisbet remarks on the President's futile negotiations with the Canadian governor to end conflicts with the Indians. He mentions an intended duel between Mr. Jamieson and Cook the Methodist, and supposes that the Gazette will print something about it. Nisbet argues that it is Europe's duty to crush expanding French military and ideological influence.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, October 29, 1793 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    Nisbet facetiously discusses French incursions into Holland, commenting, "the Army under Pichegru have made a full stop on the Borders of Holland, some say owing to hydrophobia & others to Dysentery, which has reduced many to a State of Equality."
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, November 8, 1793 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Nisbet is concerned about conflicting reports about General Wayne's success in the West [Northwest Indian War]. He complains about conflicts between American generals, including General Mifflin. Nisbet mocks Findley and Brackenridge's diametrically opposed views on Indian affairs and remarks on Jacobin clubs in America. He also mentions a ship that has returned from St. Domingo [Dominican Republic].
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, January 27, 1794 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Nisbet writes that the Republic of France has a great victory over Marie Antoniette, widow of the late tyrant of France, whose picture is still to be seen in the senate house of congress, as they thought him to Benefactor of America. This victory has given great joy to the friend of Liberty and Equality, both in France and America and is expected to contribute as much to the success of the French Convention, as it has done to their reputation for Generality, and Justice.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, October 29, 1794 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    Nisbet is astonished in the age of reason that has done so much deserved honor to true republicans, any should choose to run away from promotions. But the modesty of some Gentlemen seems to be equal to all their other virtues.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, January 13, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    Nisbet congratulates Addison on his address published in the Gazette. He goes on to discuss the situation with the militia and Nisbet inquires about troop presence in Addison's region, and describes plans of The Democratic Society to publish a counter-revolutionary paper. Nisbet criticizes Brackenridge for spinning the truth about Dutch land purchases in Allegheny County.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, February 20, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    This letter satirizes Gallatin and the treaty under debate in Congress. Nisbet refers to congressman as " prisoners in Philadelphia."
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, March 4, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    Nisbet says that the truth is that this country is in much greater danger of undergoing a revolution a revolution, from the diffusion of French Doctrines, than Great Britain can possible be, as the government there never gave them any countenance and discovered from the beginning their pernicious tendencies. Whereas our government from all total want of sense, could not discern that these doctrines tended to be destructive of all Governments.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, April 18, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    Nisbet describe England gain from the French reign over Holland. England is said to have, than all our democratic societies, being now without a rival in the commercial world, though fie this advantage are indebted to the French.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, June 17, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    Nisbet mentions mutual acquaintances and discusses events in France concerning [Charles] Pichegru, and the hypocrisy of American alliance with Prussia. He closes with satirical remarks about the Treaty with Britain.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, August 6, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    Nisbet preys that the country does not have a civil war, otherwise it is possible that America will be a first bone of Contention among the powers of Europe, if their present difference were settled. We are a divided people without wisdom, strength or Union and would be easy pray to the sans culottes, if they were able to establish their republic.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, October 3, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    Nisbet describes increased local interest in politics in opposition to Jay's Treaty. He discusses events surrounding dispatches by M. Fauchet intercepted by the British and forwarded to the President. According to the dispatches, Fauchet had been funneling large sums to Secretary of State Mr. [Edmund] Randolph and American Democrats. Randolph resigned after the dispatches were discovered.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, February 24, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    Nisbet writes to Addison giving him consolation on the sudden death of his son. He also address activates such as purchasing land in the western territories and a bought of the yellow fever going around.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, April 25, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    Describe that the price of grain is triple to what they were before the reign of Liberty and Equality. Also mentioning that the British be deprived of an opportunity of getting their debt by treaty, must operate payment to themselves by taking American vessels.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, June 17, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    Nisbet write to Addison that he ought to now be afraid to writing him, or to write to Addison with great reverence, as you are a man famous in history, Nisbet says famous in history for the Insurrection, which is in many respects the most wonderful.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, October 26, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    Nisbet says that the democrats in Philadelphia are busily employed in procuring Mr. Jefferson to be elected president of the United States and enabling the French to conquer Great Britain, Portugal, and Switzerland before the approaching winter reserving the conquest of Germany, Poland, Russia, and China till the next campaign.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, December 3, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    Nisbet describe that the drought was long and severe and the sovereign people are very happy notwithstanding as they are in hopes of getting a Sans Culottes president and a war with great Britain by which they are in expectation of producing a revolution in both countries and extending the interest of Liberty and Equality.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, January 31, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    Nisbet talks about the burning of cities and in Philadelphia. It is in this manner that our democrats show their love to their country by flattering its enemies, and endeavoring to ruin its friends. I would no be surprised to hear that they assist the French in setting fire to our towns, so entirely are they devoted to that terrible nation.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, February 23, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    Nisbet describes that our government has offended the terrible nation, who takes thus method of being revenged on us as well as that of capturing our ships. If the French should obtain Louisiana from the Spaniards, and Canada and Nova Scotia from England in the Event of a Peace, the United States would quickly become a municipality of the terrible republic.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, June 9, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    Nisbet tells Addison that his daughter has arrived ahead of schedule for her visit at their home and will be treated as one of family. Nisbet also said that the next session of congress is likely to be a turbulent one.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, July 31, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    In this brief letter, Nisbet discusses his son's weather-delayed plans to travel west and satirizes Findley, Gallatin, and the French Revolution.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, April 12, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    Nisbet describes in a private letter to Addison of his son's twelve year battle with alcohol. After taking one glass, nothing is to easy as to take another and so on without limits. Nibet's son is staying under the Addison care as Nibet asked that Addison to impart some advice of which his son would be more apt to follow because of his respect for Addison.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, August 31, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    In his letter to Addison, Nisbet discusses his son's request for money and depends on Addison to determine his son's financial situation. He discusses an illness in the East and refers to American sympathizers of the French Revolution as "Democ-Rats."
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, September 9, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    Nisbet sends money to Addison to give his son who is under Addison's care. However Nisbet tells Addison to only give the money to his son if he deserves the twenty dollar note on the agreement that he continues to remain sober.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, October 30, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    Nisbet inquires about is wayward son under Addison's care and again sends a twenty dollar note to be given to his son. He then goes on to talk about world events such as the rebuilding of the Turkish Empire and College of Cardinals election of a new Pope.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, November 5, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    This personal letter discuses the increasingly unstable behavior of Nisbet's son, who has been staying with Addison. He concurs that Addison should put the son out of his house, but asks that Addison help him find new lodging and continue to keep an eye on him.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, November 27, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    Nisbet thanks Addison for dealing with his son, and admits to sending his son more money. Upon Nisbet's request, a young woman and family friend named Miss McFarquhar talked with his son, but to no effect. He also writes that his newborn grandson died, and his wife is still ill.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, February 17, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 72)
    Nisbet continues to inquire about his alcoholic son who has stopped writing to him. He mentions a neighbor whipping a slave and Nisbet's wife and another woman successively trying to intervene. He asks Addison to use the enclosed twenty dollars to keep his son housed and fed.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, February 24, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    Nisbet writes to Addison to apologize for his son. Nisbet, desperately and facetiously, proposes to hire a woman of bad reputation to verbally abuse his son in order to reform him.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, March 10, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 74)
    Nisbet continues to inquire about his son. He thanks Addison for giving Nisbet's money to the son's landlady. He discusses his son's debts from drinking on borrowed money. Nisbet pledges to continue sending Addison money to pay for his son's room and board, but not his alcohol.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, April 5, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 75)
    Nisbet writes that he is in ill health and bad spirits. He inquires about Gallatin's recent speech, references a Spanish agreement to cede Louisiana and Florida to the French, and touches on Continental politics with sarcasm.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, April 30, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 76)
    Nisbet requests that Addison pass an enclosed letter on to his son and relates his plans to travel to Philadelphia with his wife to recover their health. Nisbet shares that a letter he received from Findley complained about Addison.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, November 19, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 77)
    Nisbet informs Addison that his son has finally written and informed him of his debts. Nisbet writes that he has sent his son money and asks Addison to make sure it is spent on debts.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, December 15, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 78)
    Nisbet talks about his son's recovery from alcohol and his health has much improved. He spends his time now reading law books instead of novels. Nisbet also mentions that Congress is trifling about the Alien and Sedition Act, but the defense of the country is entirely forgotten.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, February 25, 1799 (Box 1, Folder 79)
    Nisbet discusses friends and happenings in the House of Representatives. He is disappointed that the president has sent another ambassador to France. Nisbet is concerned the French will take advantage of the political divisions between the North and South.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, March 18, 1799 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    Nisbet mainly describes that a war has broken out in Germany and 23,000 French soldiers have been killed near the Rhine, among who is said to be General Jourdan. Nothing is to be said of the troops of the King of Naples, so that perhaps you may soon hear of the Pope of Rome.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, May 3, 1799 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    Nisbet believes that the war in Europe could last until the end of the year as in any proceeding, the French will find or make enemies as long as any inhabitants are found on the face of the Earth, that possess any properties. The Confusions in Ireland have been renewed, on occasion of the proposed union with England, though the English Ministry has abandoned this project for the present.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, November 9, 1799 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    Nisbet writes about being indebt due to this wretched and worthless son who as begun drink hard spirits once again. He feels shame and disgrace has been brought on his family due to his son's activities. Nisbet feel if he could purchase a passenger trip back to Scotland he would soon go back as a venture, as he can not live in disgrace.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, September 19, 1803 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    Nisbet states if Bonaparte miscarries in his designs on Great Britain, as I hope he undoubtedly will, it will be hurtful to his interest in France, if not fatal. He soon to have enough to do at present to turn the attention of the French to many points abroad, in order to make their slavery at home. But as he is at odds, with his general, it is not probable that his attempts against Germany, Italy, Egypt, Great Britain, Spain, and Portugal will all of them be equally successful, though he is supported by the powerful Batavian Republic.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, March 16, 1802 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    In this letter, Nisbet shows distaste for student unrest, relating it to public criticism of the judiciary and French slave revolts.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, June 7, 1802 (Box 2, Folder 85)
    Nisbet writes that his son is in the Pennsylvania hospital, and his debtors are threatening to sue Nisbet personally. He is doubtful that the case will succeed, but he asks Addison to advise.
  - Charles Nisbet to Alexander Addison, February 12, 1803 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    Nisbet encourages Addison to write a fair treatment of a judge who lost his office after an incident involving a French citizen. [This comment may refer to Addison's own impeachment]. He mentions trouble with the trustees of Dickinson College and discusses unsatisfactory French influence on American politics.
- Miscellaneous, undated; IV.
  This series contains a set of two artistic renderings of Addison's profile, and an 1807 letter to Jonathan Smith.
  - Alexander Addison to Jonanthan Smith, March 19, 1803 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    Addison writes that Mr. Monroe's mission is considered as a wonderful stroke in Politics, as while he is negotiating the French will be acting and taking possession of Louisiana, so that the citizens will arrive at St. Cloud, just in time to congratulate Bonaparte on the addition made to the territories of the republic by the possession of Louisiana and to entreat him not to turn his arms against the United States till Mr. Jefferson's Presidency is expired. The French put in possessions of Mexico and Peru that the Unites States say have the inestimable privilege of being the last devoured by the Great Nation.
  - Alexander Addison to Jonathan Smith, May 20, 1807 (Box 2, Folder 88)
    Addison writes to Smith regarding a transfer of funds facilitated by Mr. McKnight of Shippensburgh.
  - Silhouette, undated (Box 2, Folder 89)
    The folder contains two small, profile silhouettes, one rendered in charcoal and one in ink. Both are labeled as Judge Addison.
  - Manuscript fragment (4 pages), c 1805 (Box 2, Folder 90)
    A portion of an unpublished autobiographical account scathingly condemning Judge Hugh H. Brackenridge for orchestrating a betrayal resulting in Addison's impeachment by trail in 1803.